Finding Aid for the Livingston Gearhart Recordings, 1949-2001
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Livingston Gearhart Recordings, 1949-2001
Mus. Arc. 23.4
Gearhart, Livingston
3 boxes ( 41 items )
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The collection of Livingston Gearhart Recordings contains reel to reel and cassette tapes, compact discs, and LPs containing music composed, arranged, or performed by Livingston Gearhart.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Livingston and Pamela Gearhart. Some items acquired by the Music Library separately.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Alternate Forms
Reel to reel tape items (1-5) have been reformatted to digital files. Archival and service copies are housed adjacent to the related items.
Biographical Note
Livingston Gearhart was born in Buffalo, New York December 31, 1916. His mother was Lillian Hawley Gearhart, a pianist who had studied for a year under Theodor Leschetizky in Vienna. As a child Gearhart studied piano, oboe, violoncello, and sang in church choirs in Buffalo and New York City. He graduated from high school in East Orange, New Jersey in 1935. He entered Curtis Institute of Music in Philadelphia in 1935 as an oboe student of Marcel Tabuteau. In his second year he switched his major to study composition with Rosario Scalero and piano with Nadia Reisenberg.
Gearhart sailed to Paris aboard the Normandie in 1937. With generous support from a wealthy American expatriate, he was able to enroll at the Conservatoire Américain de Fontainebleau where he studied music theory and composition with Nadia Boulanger. He was awarded the school's 2nd prize (no first prize was awarded that year) in the Prix Stovall composition competition in 1937. While in Paris he also met Igor Stravinsky, Darius Milhaud, Robert Casadesus, pianist Isidore Philipp, and his future wife and duo-piano partner, Virginia Clotfelter. He and Virginia performed their debut in Paris February 1, 1939 at the Salle Chopin. They received good reviews and were then able to give concerts in other French and Swiss locations until the conditions of World War II caused them to return to the United States.
Virginia Clotfelter adopted the professional name Morley and married Gearhart February 28, 1940 in New York City. They worked at numerous venues, including the Hotel Brevoort and the club, Ruban Bleu, both operated by Herbert Jacoby. The pair spent the summers of 1942 and 1943 as Artists-in-Residence at Morley's alma mater, Mills College in Oakland, California. While there Gearhart was able to study composition with Darius Milhaud. The Budapest String Quartet was also in residence at Mills College during those years and Gearhart and Morley formed friendships with quartet members Alexander and Mischa Schneider. The Morley Gearhart duo was very successful, performing works by Milhaud, Norman Dello Joio, David Diamond, and Stravinsky's Concerto per due pianoforte soli.
The duo received contracts with Columbia Concerts and the Fred Waring Show that extended from 1943-1954. During 1941 to 1954, the two-piano team of Morley and Gearhart performed over 2000 concerts throughout the US and Canada in addition to recording for Columbia Masterworks and Decca Records. Included among the many concert dates was a performance by the duo at the White House for President Dwight D. Eisenhower in 1953. During this period Gearhart also worked as a staff arranger for the Fred Waring Show.
A two-CD retrospective released in 2001, Morley and Gearhart Rediscovered by Ivory Classics, features 22 of Gearhart's two-piano arrangements. Some of these arrangements survive at Penn State in their collection, Fred Waring's America. In many cases Gearhart never fully wrote out his part of a duo so no written arrangement survives.
Livingston Gearhart's output contains several collections written for pedagogical purposes. The first of Gearhart's these works to be published was Clarinet Sessions in 1945. That was followed by similar collections for trumpet, violin, flute, and duos. Gearhart's entire compositional and arranging output includes 400-500 works (counting individual works within the collections).
Gearhart returned to Buffalo in 1955 and was appointed to the faculty of the music department at the University of Buffalo. After a divorce from Virginia Morley, he married violinist and conductor Pamela Gerhart (not a misspelling) in 1955. He taught various courses in keyboard, theory, and orchestration until his retirement in 1985.
Livingston Gearhart had four children: Paul, born to Virginia Morley Gearhart; Kim, Martha, and Fritz, born to Pamela Gearhart. Livingston Gearhart died in Buffalo at the age of 79 on July 14, 1996.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains reel-to-reel and cassette tapes of music composed, arranged, or performed by Livingston Gearhart. One cassette contains a recording of his memorial service. Two compact discs contain reissues of recordings issued by the duo-piano team, Morley and Gearhart. The long playing recordings consist of three Fred Waring recordings with arrangements by Gearhart, the original Morley and Gearhart duo-piano recordings, and seven recordings of other compositions and arrangements by Gearhart.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series:
I. Reel to reel tapes
II. Cassettes
III. Compact discs
IV. Long playing records
V. Additions
Container List
- Reel to reel tapes, 1950-1979, I.; Items 1-6
  - Gearhart, Livingston Parade of the cliches, undated, 1 3-inch reel of tape (Box 1, Item 1)
  - Brubeck, Dave Watusi drums, after 1966?, 1 3-inch reel of tape (Box 1, Item 2)
    Arrangement of Dave Brubeck's Watusi drums by Livingston Gearhart for concert band.
  - FW & PA's Rudolph, the red-nose reindeer, undated, 1 5-inch reel of tape (Box 1, Item 3)
    Arrangement by Livingston Gearhart for Fred Waring and the Pennsylvanians for voices, instrumental accompaniment, and sound effects. The arrangement appeared on Fred Waring's Christmas albums, Twas the night before Christmas and Meaning of Christmas.
  - Gearhart, Livingston Variations on an American air, August 14, 1962, 1 5-inch reel of tape; Chautauqua Symphony Orchestra, Walter Hendl, conductor and piano soloist, Chautauqua, New York. Based on Yankee Doodle. (Box 1, Item 4)
    7 ½ ips, Full track
  - Gearhart, Livingston YD in Ithaca, October 19, 1979, 1 7-inch reel of tape; Gearhart's Variations on an American air performed by the Ithaca College Orchestra in Ford Auditorium, Ithaca College, Ithaca, New York. It is based on Yankee Doodle. (Box 1, Item 5)
    7 ½ ips, 2 channels
  - Gearhart, Livingston Frontier U., undated, 1 10-inch reel of tape; Music for a documentary film, Decade for decision. It was about education in the United States and used the University of Buffalo as an example. The film was produced for RKO-Pathe in 1957 by Jay Bonafield and was written by Ardis Smith. Reformatted to compact disc April 16, 2004. (Box 2, Item 6)
- Cassettes, 1979-1993, II.; Items 7-8
  - Gearhart, Livingston Variations on an American air, October 19, 1979, 1 cassette; Ithaca College Orchestra, Pamela Gearhart, conductor. With commentary by the composer. (Box 2, Item 7)
  - Livingston Gearhart Memorial Service, October 6, 1996, 1 cassette (Box 2, Item 8)
- Compact discs, 1990-2001, III.; Items 9-11
  - Gearhart, Livingston Variations on an American air, 1977 or 1979, 1 compact disc; Writing on CD states "Ithaca College 1977". Ithaca College Orchestra, Pamela Gearhart, conductor, with Livingston Gearhart as piano soloist and narrator. (Box 2, Item 9)
  - Americans in Paris: Morley & Gearhart, duo-pianists University Park, Pennsylvania: Pennsylvania State University, 1990, 1 compact disc; Mastered by Digi-Rom. (Box 2, Item 10)
  - Virginia Morley and Livingston Gearhart rediscovered Columbus, Ohio: Ivory Classics, 2001, 2 compact discs; Publisher's number: 64405-72004 (Box 2, Item 11)
- Long playing records, 1949-1980, IV.; Items 12-24
  - 1974 NYSSMA Thousand Islands High School all state music festival Clarence, New York: Mark Custom Recording Division, 1974, 2 sound discs; Publisher number: MC 5969. (Box 2, Item 12)
    12 inch, 33 1/3 stereophonic recording
    Side one (of four) contains Gearhart's arrangement of Sergei Rachmaninoff's Vocalise and his own composition, Overture on Jewish theme[s], performed by the festival's orchestra, conducted by Pamela Gearhart.
  - Massachusetts Music Educators Association fifth annual Southeastern District junior high concert East Bridgewater, Massachusetts: John Brooks Custom Recording, 1978, 2 sound discs; Publisher number: JB7816. Concert recorded March 11, 1978 at Silver Lake Regional High School, Pembroke, Massachusetts. (Box 2, Item 13)
    Side one (of three) contains Gearhart's arrangement of Sergei Rachmaninoff's Vocalise, op. 34, performed by the festival's orchestra, conducted by Pamela Gearhart.
  - Ithaca College Sectional All-State Music Festival Clarence, New York: Mark Custom Recording Division, 197-, 1 sound disc; Publisher number: MC-5367. (Box 2, Item 14)
    Contains Gearhart's Overture on Jewish themes, performed by the festival's orchestra, conducted by Pamela Gearhart.
  - Orchfare, volume 1: the Ithaca College string and symphony orchestras Delaware Water Gap, Pennsylvania: Shawnee Press, 1981, 1 sound disc; Publisher number: P 652. (Box 2, Item 15)
    Contains Gearhart's String Mix no. 1, performed by the Ithaca College String Orchestra, conducted by Pamela Gearhart.
    Program notes consist of miniature scores of recorded works.
  - Orchfare, volume 2: the Ithaca College String and Symphony Orchestras Delaware Water Gap, Pennsylvania: Shawnee Press, 1982, 1 sound disc; Publisher number: P 679. (Box 2, Item 16)
    Contains Gearhart's arrangement for orchestra of Sergei Prokofiev's Marche, op. 12, no. 1 from his Ten Pieces for piano, performed by the festival's orchestra, conducted by Pamela Gearhart.
  - I hear music [New York]: Decca, [1952], 1 sound disc; Publisher number: DL 5408. (Box 2, Item 17)
    10 inch, 33 1/3 monaural recording
    Performed by Fred Waring and his Pennsylvanians. Gearhart is mentioned in the program notes as one of Waring's arrangers but is not cited specifically for any of the works.
  - Longines Symphonette Society presents Fred Waring and The Pennsylvanians, This is my country Larchmont, New York: Longines Symphonette Society, 196-?, 1 sound disc; Publisher number: SYS 5276. (Box 2, Item 18)
    Contains Gearhart's arrangement of Dry bones, not cited on album.
  - Fred Waring and The Pennsylvanians in hi-fi Hollywood, California: Capitol, 1967, 1 sound disc; Publisher's number: W-845. (Box 2, Item 19)
    12 inch, 33 1/3 recording
    Contains Gearhart's arrangement of Dry bones.
  - Again! Virtuosity at two pianos: Morley and Gearhart encores Delaware Water Gap, Pennsylvania: Omnisound, 1981, 1 sound disc; Publisher's number: N–1030. (Box 2, Item 20)
    Five additional copies.
  - Two piano artistry of Morley and Gearhart rediscovered Delaware Water Gap, Pennsylvania: Omnisound, 1978, 1 sound disc; Publisher's number: –1017. (Box 2, Item 21)
    Two additional copies.
  - Night life on two pianos: Morley and Gearhart duo-pianists New York: Columbia, 1949, 1 sound disc; Publisher's number: ML 2033. (Box 2, Item 22)
  - Americans in Paris: Morley and Gearhart, duo-pianists New York: Columbia, 1951, 1 sound disc; Publisher's number: ML 2197. (Box 2, Item 23)
  - Songs recorded from Livingston Gearhart's A singing bee Delaware Water Gap, Pennsylvania: Shawnee Press, 196-?, 1 sound disc; Publisher's number: XTV 25573. (Box 2, Item 24)
  - 50th anniversary jubilee concert, College of Arts and Sciences, State University of New York at Buffalo, 1964, 1 sound disc; Williamsville, New York: Century Custom Recording Service Publisher's number: 18669. (Box 2, Item 25)
    Contains Gearhart's arrangements of the University at Buffalo Alma Mater for chorus and for band.
- Additions, circa 1950-2006, V.; Item 26-40
  Recordings received after processing of the original collection was completed. Included are recordings of the Morley and Gearhart piano duo, a live performance by Livingston and Pamela Gearhart, and recordings of arrangements and compositions by Gearhart.
  Arranged in two subseries:
  A. Performances by Livingston Gearhart
  B. Compositions and arrangements by Livingston Gearhart
  - Performances by Livingston Gearhart, 1950-1960, V.A; Item 26-31 (6 cassettes)
    Recordings of the Morley and Gearhart piano duo, Fred Waring television shows, and with violinist Pamela Gearhart.
    Arranged in chronological order.
    - Devil's dream, from G.E. TV show, 1950-1959, 1 cassette; Issued by Shawnee Press. (Box 3, Item 26)
      1. 2/19/59 (3:15) -- 2. 10/29/50 (3:15) -- 3. 10/21/50 (3:00).
    - Morley and Gearhart Potsdam Civic Center, 1951 October 5, 2 cassettes; With spoken commentary. (Box 3, Item 27-28)
    - Morley and Gearhart un-released material, circa 1951, 1 cassette (Box 3, Item 29)
      Jesu, joy of man's desiring -- Rachmaninoff Prelude -- Viennese clock -- Nola -- Minute waltz -- Tea for two -- Kitten on the keys -- Mountain tune -- With a song in my heart.
    - Morley and Gearhart un-used material from Columbia tapes, circa 1951, 1 cassette; Provided by Fred Waring's America, Penn State. (Box 3, Item 30)
      Parlez-moi d'amour -- La tirelitentaine -- Debussy: Fetes -- Baby boogie -- Stormy weather -- Body and soul.
    - Milhaud: PG and LG, 1963?, 1 cassette (Box 3, Item 31)
      Live performance of Darius Milhaud's Suite for clarinet, violin, and piano, op. 157b, with Livingston Gearhart, piano and Pamela Gearhart, violin. The performance is possibly that of 1963 June 9 with Hazel Colley, clarinet.
  - Compositions and arrangements by Livingston Gearhart, 1961-circa 2006, V.B; Item 32-41 (9 cassettes and 1 compact disc)
    Recordings include compilations of Gearhart arrangements and a demo version of Sax sessions.
    Arranged in alphabetical order by title.
    - Gearhart tape I, circa 1996, 1 cassette (Box 3, Item 32)
      Kyrie -- Short suite -- ALA fanfare -- We shall overcome -- Variations on an American air.
    - Gearhart tape II, circa 1996, 1 cassette (Box 3, Item 33)
      Holst variations -- Brubeck Ostinato -- Theme X -- Ce soir.
    - Gearhart tape III, circa 1996, 1 cassette (Box 3, Item 34)
      Mendelssohn -- Bach Arioso -- Ravel Pavane -- Bach Cantata #54 -- Bach Fantasia -- Bach Old year -- Boccherini Quintet -- MLK.
    - Gearhart tape V, circa 1996, 1 cassette (Box 3, Item 35)
      L. Gearhart accompaniments for beginning Suzuki pieces (5) plus Fioco Allegro.
    - Humor in music, 1961, 1 cassette (Box 3, Item 36)
      With narration by Livingston Gearhart.
    - London Bridge variations by Livingston Gearhart, circa 2006, 1 compact disc; Performed by the Oregon String Quartet. (Box 3, Item 37)
    - Sax sessions demo, circa 1987, 1 cassette; Performed by Kelland Thomas. (Box 3, Item 38)
    - Short suite, undated, 1 cassette (Box 3, Item 39)
    - Variations on Yankee doodle, undated, 1 cassette; Narrated by Livingston Gearhart. (Box 3, Item 40)
    - We shall overcome: orchestra and chorus, undated, 1 cassette (Box 3, Item 41)
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
Waring, Virginia; Gearhart, Pamela
Subjects
Piano music (Pianos (2)); Composers--New York (State)--Buffalo; Orchestral music; Orchestral music, Arranged; Vocal music
Genres
Sound recordings
Associated Material
Additional Guides
Items 1-24 in the collection are cataloged in WorldCat and are available in BISON, the online catalog for the University at Buffalo Libraries, by performing a "Title begins with" search under "Livingston Gearhart Recordings".
Related Resources
Related Resources in the Music Library
Livingston Gearhart Papers, 1933-1997
Mus. Arc. 23.1
Contains Gearhart's vitae, prose writings, correspondence, programs, clippings, and teaching materials.
Livingston Gearhart Collection of Scores, 1945-1993
Mus. Arc. 23.2
Contains 676 folders of Gearhart's compositions, arrangements, and annotated scores.
Livingston Gearhart Collection of Photographs,1896-1941
Mus. Arc. 23.3
Collection of 192 images, including photographs of Nadia Boulanger and her summer class of 1938, Gearhart and his first wife, Virginia Morley (Waring) at Mills College in California, with composer Darius Milhaud and his family, and the Budapest String Quartet. The collection also includes four photographs of composer Johannes Brahms in 1896. Also available as a digital collection in
University at Buffalo Libraries Digital Collections
.